[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host bridget shamanith and
today my guest is abby noda abbey led
engineering teams for over six years
before founding pull panda a developer
productivity tool used by over 7000
developers
which was acquired by github in 2019 at
github he led research collaborations
with dr nicole forskrim mckenzie and
microsoft research which was the impetus
for founding his new company dx abby
welcome to software engineering radio is
there anything i missed in your bio that
you would like to add now i think you
covered it thanks so much for having me
thank you we will be talking today about
developer experience commonly referred
to as dx once we have gained an
understanding about what dx is we will
jump into various topics covering
measurement influencing factors
strategies to improve dx the barriers
encountered coping mechanisms adopted by
developers and developer productivity
let's start with the basics abby what is
developer experience and why is it
important sure well just in the past
couple years i think dx or developer
experience has really become a buzzword
and so it's really getting thrown out a
lot
now i think the most common definitions
of developer experience really boil down
to two you often hear people referring
to
developer experience in the context of
vendor solutions and external tools
meaning these are companies for example
companies like stripe that build
products for developers and they talk
about developer experience in terms of
the user experience of their products
for developers the other context in
which developer experience is used as
internally and so if you look across the
industry there are more and more
teams that are called developer
experience teams and these teams look
internally within their companies and at
the experiences of their employees who
are developers
and so when we talk about developer
experience today we're talking about
this latter category we're talking about
the holistic lived experiences of
developers in their day-to-day work
working on professional teams and really
i think developer experience is about
all the different points of friction
that these developers encounter in their
work and these things span
from tools to the processes to the
culture of their organization and so
improving developer experience is really
about empowering developers to do their
best work so they can ultimately deliver
the best results for their companies and
teams i like the phrase lived experience
of developers so to put it another way i
would say it's the quality of engineers
quality of life for engineers would that
sum it up yeah quality of life
you know for developers quality of life
means different things right again
developer experience is really
a collection of things that affect those
live experiences so quality of life i
think would be yeah i think that would
be an acceptable way to sum it up right
does dx become more important as teams
work in a remote or hybrid model well
certainly so i think developer
experience like many aspects of sort of
the lived experience of employees
becomes more difficult to understand and
stay aware of as
teams shift to hybrid and remote working
models and so you know really
i think developer experience is
important regardless of whether you're
co-located or remote because
developers are ultimately the the
lifeblood of today's modern digital
economy and of course companies invest
so much money into developers salaries
and tools
and at the same time we know there's so
much room for improving
engineering efficiency and developer
happiness a few years ago stripe
published this study that global gdp is
reduced by over 300 billion dollars per
year due to developer and efficiency
and so developer experience isn't just
this kind of feel-good topic about
quality of life so to speak but it's
also critical to the bottom line for for
business
interesting so besides the bottom line
what are some other benefits of an
enhanced dx sure so first of all when we
say bottom line you know what does that
mean so you know we have research
showing that developer experience is a
top predictor of developer productivity
and satisfaction which of course these
things correlate to the bottom line of
companies
so we see that companies with you know
top quartile developer experience not
only
outperformed their competition in terms
of productivity and their ability to
innovate faster but also ultimately that
business performance whether that's
commercial or non-commercial goals
aside from kind of things pertaining to
productivity and money
there's also today this big war for
talent going on and so this ability to
attract and retain top talent
is probably just as if not more
important than how quickly you can
deliver and developer experience is of
course so key to keeping your developers
happy and engaged within your
organization
i did have a related question around
the retention by using dx as one of the
differentiating factors by companies so
is there a
leak table for dx where companies you
know you can if you are
looking for a job you can look up how
how is that company performing on dx and
that influences your decision whether to
take that job or not and equally from a
different angle if you are a company how
do you go out and tell developers that
you've got a great dx
sure well today there's not some formal
way in which dx is
tracked and shared to
candidates but i think sort of
unofficially or informally
dx is really important to candidates who
are looking for new job opportunities i
think developers are always sort of
aware of where other good developers are
going to work and what they're hearing
about those companies and much of what
you hear is about the developer
experience it's that it's that ability
to
do great work
and to you know work collaboratively and
be successful as a team and be empowered
with great tools and the ability to work
highly effectively
and so while it's not something that's
necessarily
shared and tracked in some kind of
objective way it's definitely something
that's talked about a lot and you i
think you're seeing that trend more and
more companies are
really looking for ways to differentiate
themselves and of course you hear
companies sharing you know we got ranked
you know top 10 places to work things
like that but you know within sort of
one-on-one conversations in the
recruiting process the the internal
developer experience is definitely a
huge point of emphasis in order to
make a place attractive for developers
to work and i'm sorry could you repeat
the second question so the second part
was if you are a company and you really
move the needle in terms of improving
your dx internally how do you make sure
that you know you use that to advertise
and attract more talent
sure today a lot of that again as i was
mentioning is captured sort of
informally so
throughout the interview process
it's usually becomes sort of a two-way
information sharing sort of
process where candidates are being
interviewed but candidates are also
interviewing the company and they often
get to interact with
developers on multiple teams leaders in
multiple parts of the organization
they get to
see blog posts and open source code
written by people who who work there so
i think candidates are able to get a
pretty good
pulse or a sense of what the developer
experience looks like just by asking
questions and you know as we'll kind of
i'm sure talk about later you know
asking questions is really the key to
how we understand developer experience
within organizations there are certainly
sort of you know system-based metrics
that you can look at i mean candidates
could ask how quickly do your builds
finish but really to understand
developer experience holistically you
need to look at
self-reported data from developers
so build time is a question that you
could ask what are some other questions
that a potential candidate could ask the
companies they're interviewing with to
get a gauge an understanding about how
the dx is sure that's a great question
you know i haven't been in that position
in a little bit
but you know based on our research i can
say
that you know there's a whole
range of factors that affect developer
experience and and a subset of those are
things that are very top of mind for
developers so
i think a common question would be
around the development environment what
is the process you have to go through to
actually
set up code locally run it
work on it and you know create a change
then beyond that i think there's the
organizational side of making changes so
what is the review process what's the
approval process what steps you need to
go through to actually take something
you've completed and release it to
customers what's that feedback loop look
like so a lot of it has to do with this
kind of
the feedback loops that are scattered
across the development process and
experience
and asking about those and really asking
not just about
necessarily the time it takes to
complete those different
aspects but
moreover
you know are they frustrating what's the
experience like do they is it a joy to
do work at this company or is it does it
feel like a slog some excellent tips
thanks now that we have a good
understanding about dx let's dig a bit
deeper starting with measurement
what are the different methodologies for
measuring dx
yeah this is one of the reasons why dx
is so important right because
in general this problem of measurement
or measuring productivity has been such
an elusive problem for engineering
leaders for decades
uh companies spend millions of dollars
on developers but they don't have clear
indicators on how effective their
developers are or where they need to
invest in order to improve so just
generally speaking we as an industry
really desperately need more effective
approaches to measurement
when you talk about developer experience
specifically there are really
two ways to measure it there are
certainly aspects of developer
experience that can be under understood
by looking at our systems so the example
we've already talked about for example
how long developers wait for builds to
complete that's something you can if you
have a well-built pipeline
you can look at the stats and it'll tell
you how long builds take to complete but
really the only way to measure
experience holistically is to get
self-reported data from developers and
i'll give you one example so
code review right so
we know that the time spent waiting for
code reviews can be
a major point of frustration and delay
for developers and this is an example
where there are
two
acceptable ways to measure you could
look at
systems so you could try to look at
your jira board or your github pull
request data to understand how long it
takes for things to kind of move through
the process and move through the systems
but you could also
ask developers to share self-reported
data on how long they wait or maybe not
just how long they wait but also
you know how long they're blocked or how
much they're frustrated by the process
and that's really so important because
one of the problems i think we have
today in the way we attempt to measure
not only experience but just things in
the development process as a whole is
that we miss
the business context we miss the root
cause right when we look at certain
types of metrics they tell us what's
happening but they don't actually take
into account what the world looks like
for a developer and as a result
a lot of these measures don't really
provide an accurate or meaningful in the
trenches view of
what's causing friction for teams and
developers
so if i got it right there are broadly
two different methodologies one is the
system metrics and the other one is
self-reported measures but it would be
wrong to just use the system metrics
because that will not give a true
picture of what's happening on the
ground so you need to in addition to the
system metrics also need the
self-reported measures yeah i mean i
would go one step further and and say
that really there's there's a very
limited amount of
information you can capture from the
system metrics alone both because of the
challenge in accurately instrumenting
our systems but also because the systems
only touch really a fraction of the
things that affect developer experience
you know earlier we talked about how
developer experience was not just about
the build tools but it was really about
the end-to-end experience of building
and developing and releasing software
and working across the team or multiple
teams to accomplish that goal and so
when you think about what's involved in
the developer experience as a whole it
goes far beyond just the time spent
waiting for builds or the time
it takes for a pull request to go
through a system you only get a very
limited understanding of the developer
experience if you only look at system
data and so really
organizations need to move toward
getting self-reported data from
developers in order to get a holistic
understanding of developer experience
how should leaders think about the
importance of measuring and focusing on
developer experience versus other
metrics they may already track
yeah well if you talk to most leaders
about
engineering or developer productivity
type metrics most still feel pretty lost
and frustrated with the status quo right
i mentioned earlier that we really as an
industry need more effective approaches
to measurement and it's i think it's
really interesting to look at the way we
how we measure has evolved
if you look back to the 90s or even 80s
and 2000s
there was a big emphasis on measuring
output things like lines of code or
velocity points those are the most
common ones
but you know developers understood and
many leaders quickly understood that
those types of
output measures don't account for the
complexity or nuance of engineering work
for example
shipping something that has more lines
of code is not better than shipping
something that has less lines of code
and it doesn't tell you how difficult
that task was
moving forward
more recently there's been this shift
towards process metrics or delivery
metrics right so dora is a great example
of this metrics like lead time pull
request throughput pull request cycle
time this is what i see most companies
today focus on measuring and as
mentioned earlier there's a huge problem
with these metrics because they don't
account for the context or root cause
for example
your data might tell you that code
reviews are taking
three days to complete but if you go
talk to the team
they might tell you that that is
perfectly acceptable to them because
they work on multiple tasks at once or
lead time for example or deployment
frequency the devops
annual report says that you know elite
performers release things daily
constantly
but what if you're an ios team that has
to wait two weeks for your app to get
reviewed by apple right but that lead
time metric doesn't really speak to you
in terms of the reality of how you work
and so
there's
really i think a big need in the
industry right now for a better way to
measure and impact
engineering productivity and performance
and i think that's what developer
experience has the potential to offer
right experience
provides the true in the trenches
indicators of
the bottlenecks and performance of
developers and their teams and
you know this is so important to leaders
because as we talked about earlier not
only of course it's a top priority for
them to
maximize sort of output and productivity
and performance but it's just as much of
a priority for them to retain their
talent and keep their developers happy
and really
there's not many other ways to do that
than to focus on developer experience
and measure and improve it from what
you're saying you're saying that
developer experience measures will be
different for each team because each
team is unique and they're working on
different emergent problems and if
that's the case are we saying that it's
not possible to have a standard set of
measures for dx
it is possible to have a standard set of
but it's also important to understand
that every team is different and every
team has their own challenges and their
own unique points of friction and not
only just teams but if you go down to
the individual level
you'll find that people on the same team
can have very different
experiences
as well depending on what they're
working on so an example would be if
you're on a team you might have a senior
engineer who's
really in the role of
developing features but also supporting
the rest of the team mentoring the more
junior developers doing a lot of the
code reviews so their biggest points of
friction friction might be the amount of
time
that is taken away from them to do
mentoring type work or card review work
or just the workload in general whereas
if you were to go talk to
a junior engineer on that team they
might be really struggling with
understanding the code base or
understanding requirements for work
you know getting clear scope or being
able to reduce their work down into sort
of manageable
sizes in terms of batch size so
really
problems
come down to the individual level
and to understand them you need to look
at the individuals you need to look at
the teams then
and then you can look holistically at
the organization and what the patterns
and major themes are
can dxp compared across teams or is it
similar to a velocity which is unique to
each team and hence should not be used
to measure different teams but just the
individual team's performance over time
developer experience can definitely be
measured across teams
but like any measure you have to be
careful when doing that right you don't
want to create
unhealthy competition between teams you
also don't want to
accidentally create incentives for teams
to
sort of game their metrics
right to alter their metrics because
there is a reward for doing so and so
you
can certainly compare developer
experience across teams to help with
learning
both learning for leaders to understand
you know where
investments or support may be needed and
also learning for teams to understand
best practices and learnings from other
teams that are doing things well
but you have to be careful whenever you
are comparing
because it can create unhealthy dynamics
competition and ultimately lead to kind
of ruining the measures themselves
i thought that was a good discussion on
measurement methodologies moving on
let's talk on some of the influencing
factors that impact dx what are the most
important factors that affect dx
when we talk about factors
first of all we need to think of
there's a few things at play here so
there are
factors that affect developer experience
these are things like
code complexity or ease of release
test efficiency or having clear
direction
having good requirements
but we also know that
these factors themselves are highly
dependent on the individual like we were
just talking about and we have an
understanding of what affects how
these different factors affect an
individual and these things come down to
things such as seniority like the
example i provided earlier where more
senior developers
might be dealing with a totally
different set of problems than junior
developers
we also know that the presence of
problems
is has a huge effect on developer
experience meaning
developers feel the pain of problems
much more than they feel
the joy from there being a lack of
problems so developers will be able to
easily identify
and feel the friction from
things that are affecting them
day-to-day
another aspect of this has to do with
just kind of individual interests and
expectations
when you hire people in an organization
they come from
varying backgrounds
different previous job experiences and
so people come in with just a different
set of expectations for one developer
coming from
on-prem development and switching over
to for example cloud api development
they might feel like deploying code
once every two weeks is incredible
it might feel like magic but to someone
coming from working at a startup
but you know sas startup
they would find
that two weeks might feel really slow to
them and so a lot of developer
experience does often boil down to
the individual perceptions and
expectations of what good looks like
what factors are most influenced by
senior leadership and how can they play
a positive role in improving these
factors that impact dx
so when we look at developer experience
within organizations there's a really
interesting
set of dynamics at play so
what we typically find is that
most
issues
affecting developer experience are local
team issues meaning
they are specific to
the areas of the code that the local
team is working in it is specific to the
way that that local team works
it's specific to that the way that local
team interfaces with other teams
however there are also some aspects of
developer experience that are tend to be
more global so i think
release process
local development environment test
infrastructure those
are things that tend to be shared across
an organization
and therefore and oftentimes also owned
by a centralized team so when earlier we
talked about these developer experience
teams they're also often called
developer productivity teams or
enablement teams
most medium to large size companies have
a group that's responsible for kind of
owning and improving internal tooling
and those tools are typically used
across the company and so
when senior leaders are thinking about
how do we
improve developer experience within our
organization
it really has to be a two-pronged attack
it there needs to be a huge emphasis
placed on enabling these local
individual squads and pods to
understand their local point of friction
and improve those
at the same time there needs to be an
examination of patterns across the
organization or shared tools that may be
affecting everybody
and those may be things that can be
uniquely
impacted in a high leverage way by
senior leadership
okay so if i understood that try the
local factors will be primarily
influenced by
the team itself
whereas the
tools and the horizontal teams which
support the team which support many
teams those are the
touch points which can be influenced by
senior leadership to improve dx yeah
there's there's things that for example
senior leadership could
invest in
bringing you know purchasing a new tool
that makes releasing easier right that
would be an example of something that
senior leadership could easily influence
but there's a lot of things for example
teams that are struggling with how they
work in terms of process right product
management process or the way they
collaborate and communicate or the
workflows they have to
review and approve changes
those types of things aren't i mean
senior leadership can't
prescribe a one-size-fits-all
solution for the entire company that's
not how engineering organizations work
there's a huge
emphasis and value put on
enabling teams to be autonomous and grow
on their own and so what senior
leadership can do
to affect those types of issues is to
provide those local teams with a way to
both measure and understand their local
team problems and provide them the
support they need to make progress in
improving
those
local issues
right
how important is the code review process
for
dx code review process is something that
comes up frequently and there's a lot of
different facets of code review process
there's
the
portion of it that involves the person
who's getting their code reviewed so
developers often have frustration with
the amount of time they have to wait to
get feedback or the back and forth
that's involved in the code review
process there's also the quality of the
kurd review so
developers can feel maybe shortchanged
or frustrated with
not getting thorough
feedback about the work they do or on
the flip side sometimes developers feel
like
the feedback they get is
is too harsh or too strict right it's
it's not there's not a clear set of
expectations around what is an
acceptable level of quality or standard
for
the code they're writing and as a result
code reviews can sort of stall
then there's also the experience of the
reviewers there are often people in
roles that involve doing a lot of code
reviews for example if you're a senior
engineer or
someone who's maintaining a tool that
receives contributions from across the
company you have to do a lot of code
reviews and there can also be this
frustration with
the pro the experience of going and
reviewing other people's work is that
work well described is it you know is
the change clear and is it
what do you do when a change isn't
to a certain standard or what do you do
if a change just seems totally off so i
guess the most important thing is to
ensure that the code review process
itself is well documented people
understand its importance and the
reviewer is appreciated for taking the
time to doing the code review
yeah there's definitely a set of
trade-offs and that's one thing that's
common across
developer experience is that it's really
just a lot of trade-offs so for example
with code review there's this clear
trade-off between
the time it takes
for reviewers to complete code reviews
and the quality of the feedback right
reviewers can just hop into a pull
request or a change request and
just give a thumbs up sign
and that will allow that change to be
approved and released however was that a
thorough code review right no and so
there's this constant tension between
quality
and
flow and that's of course common across
software development
and so really
finding that right balance does involve
as you said setting
having clear process and expectations
and standards around the card review
process and how it'll be conducted
flow is seen as a key dimension for
developer productivity you just touched
on it can you help define flow
and what can be done to improve flow
besides the code review process
sure
yeah well i think there's a couple
different ways the industry thinks and
talks about flow so sometimes when
leaders talk about flow i think they're
just referring to output or throughput
how much
stuff are we outputting
right whether and how they think of that
might be in terms of
commits or
pull requests or
features
the other way
the industry thinks about flow has to do
with really the
psychology definition of flow which has
to do with
this
sort of nirvana state of creativity
immersion and engagement
and
that
anyone doing creative work can find
themselves in
and so and of course the two are related
right when your developers
can be in this flow state
they are
often more productive and able to
release more work leading to more output
and throughput
and flow and so
when we talk about that latter
definition of really helping developers
feel
immersed and engaged and in the zone if
you will again there are a number of
factors that affect this but i think one
of the most common ones is just
interruptions so we know that
interruptions
take developers and really anyone doing
creative work out of the flow of their
work
and
deeply reduce their
both the psychological state of how they
feel while they're doing the work but
also the output that they're able to
produce in addition to uninterrupted
time
flow is also affected by things like
you know how stimulated developers
actually feel with the work so are they
working on a boring mundane task that is
something they've done a thousand times
or are they working on something that's
new and where they're learning and feel
stimulated do they
get to learn
as part of their work in addition
autonomy is a big element of flow as
well so
if you're a developer you've probably
been in a situation where anytime you
try to make a change someone comes in
and tells you
to either rewrite your code or tells you
a different way of doing things and
this can be incredibly deflating right
to feel like you
don't have this freedom to
create and produce in the way that you
feels best and so
that autonomy over how things are
actually built is also a huge aspect of
enabling developers to feel in the zone
and immersed in their work and
ultimately as be as productive as they
could be now we will move on to the next
section where we'll talk about the
barriers that are there in
that stop companies or the teams from
improving developer experience
so abby what are the common barriers in
improving dx
so there's a number of barriers to
improving developer experience but it
really begins with a lack of visibility
and awareness you know as we talked
about earlier there's this huge problem
in the industry around just what to
measure
and as a result
experience is not something that
most organizations are measuring today
so they don't actually have visibility
into the types of problems that we
talked about like how many organizations
have
a good pulse on
how much developers are getting
interrupted or whether developers have
sufficient autonomy in their work or
code review quality these are things
that aren't measured today and therefore
they lack that visibility and awareness
and when problems don't have visibility
they aren't prioritized
and so that's what we see really with
developer experience if you talk to
developers across the industry and just
ask them about their work environment
you'll often hear them just
lament at the inefficiencies and the
barriers that they face on a day-to-day
basis
and just trying to do their work and of
course these frustrations ultimately
lead to them leaving their jobs or
becoming apathetic in their work and
disengaged
but those same sort of complaints and
problems often aren't raised and surface
within the organization and they're not
prioritized so this sort of inability to
understand and see and quantify problems
leads to
a lack of these problems being
prioritized and that's really
i think the first set of barriers that
organizations face now
once problems are understood because
sometimes
even if things aren't being measured
there may be an outspoken developer or
group of developers who are
pointing out problems or there may be a
team like a developer experience team
looking at friction points that exist
then there's this other problem around
buy-in and ownership right so
problems take time and money to actually
improve and organizations need to
really
understand
what the return on investment may be and
that's often really difficult for
developers to advocate for things that
sort of affect their work environment
but are a little disconnected from the
sort of day-to-day objectives of teams
which is the ship features the customers
and in addition even complicating that
further a lot of problems as we talked
about earlier are a little muddy in
terms of ownership
so there may be these tools that have a
clear owner
for example
the build systems may be owned by the
developer experience team at a company
but a lot of the problems for example
around collaboration or both within a
team or across multiple teams there's
not necessarily a clear percent
organization who is in charge of
being a steward of that problem
and as a result because there isn't a
clear owner
it can make change more difficult people
don't like where do people send their
complaints where do people have
conversations and
where
can people go to to have improvements
championed
and so you know hopefully this is a nice
little overview of the types of
challenges and barriers organizations
face when
trying to improve dx or or even getting
started with knowing that they should
improve developer experience
completely agree lack of visibility no
ownership
are very tough challenging barriers do
you feel some of the barriers have
become more pronounced in a fully remote
work setup and also in contrast have
some barriers
disappeared due to a remote setup
yeah that's a great question i think
problems with
visibility certainly
are affected by the shift to remote
working
a lot of that visibility and awareness
is
stuff that is more easily picked up when
you're working in a co-located
environment and you can
have
you know water cooler conversations with
co-workers and hear
how their day is going and what's
frustrating them
these types of problems
don't
often come up as much in
for example
asynchronous conversations or even in
retrospectives
in our conversations with developers we
find that
retrospectives are often very focused on
sort of sprint
objectives
they don't necessarily go into kind of
systemic problems with
how teams are working or how the
organization is working or
things like technical debt right those
are things that sort of persist
across
for months or even for years and those
things don't really get raised
in terms of some advantages of remote
work i do think that
elements such as work-life balance
uninterrupted time for example
in some cases have improved due to
remote working however you do actually
see some evidence of the contrary where
people are actually feeling more
interrupted
because of tools like slack and are
having more difficulty with work-life
balance because of there's not this
boundary between the office and where
they work and so you know largely i
think developer experience and
visibility into it has become even a
more difficult and challenging problem
as organizations and teams have shifted
to
to hiring and remote okay
now we'll move on to some strategies
that companies and teams and developers
can use to improve dx let's start off
with abby what are the common strategies
employed by companies to improve dx
sure so
many
companies there's been this shift
recently towards setting up
developer experience teams and i think
there's this organic trend in industry
right now where organizations are
placing more emphasis on developer
experience and one of the things that's
unique about
how they're approaching developer
experience is that a key element to it
is that they treat their developers
as if they were their customers so in
the same way that we
gather feedback from
our customers
and understand their satisfaction with
different elements of our products or
services
companies are doing the same with their
developers they're asking developers
about their satisfaction in different
areas of their experience and then
working to systematically measure and
improve those and so
organizations that are doing a good job
at
improving developer experience have some
kind of systematic approach to it they
are
have a systematic approach to measuring
on some cadence whether it's monthly or
quarterly or bi-annually they're
gathering feedback from their engineers
across
the development life cycle and across
all the different types of factors we've
talked about
and then they have a process for how
they
move the needle on those issues
and as we were talking about earlier a
key to
that last piece about moving the needle
has to do with that balance of
global
issues and points of friction and local
issues and points of friction so the
organizations that are making the
biggest improvements to developer
experience are really empowering their
local teams
to make local improvements themselves
not just the global developer experience
team making a couple improvements tools
each quarter but empowering the entire
organization and every team to be
continually improving
and they're doing that by providing
measurements and feedback systems to
those local teams so that they can have
the information they need to guide where
to improve and what actions to take
interesting i was just thinking back
about the definition you gave initially
when you mentioned dx can be considered
from two lenses one is where you have
companies building tools for developers
and then you have developer experience
which is internal to the company so when
we think about
dx
and
the strategy being employed to treat
developers as customers it's almost that
dx is moving into the cx world
where you're seeing developers as your
customers
yeah it has a lot of
similarities to
customer experience certainly user
experience
i think where that definition of
developer experience that you see
product companies and vendors use
the difference between that and internal
dx is the vendors are only looking at a
partial scope of the overall developer
experience right experience with
tools is really just one of many many
factors that affect developer experience
so really they are talking about the
same thing
but just a different scope right and
when you're thinking about developer
experience holistically it's it's really
everything everything in the work
environment that affects how developers
feel and how they approach their work
yeah i get it i think what we're saying
is that you could have a vendor build
great developer tools which gives a
great experience to the developers who
are their users but internally that
product that's being built the
developers were building it the culture
might not be great or the collaboration
might not be there and internal
developer experience could be very
different to what their cx is
absolutely tools is just a fraction of
of the picture right i mean
you can have great tools i mean we talk
to companies all the time where they
have great tools and teams don't even
use them
or they have great tools but
only half the teams use them because
half it's hard to build tools that suit
the needs of
everyone across the company and so
and when we talk to developers tools
don't often necessarily come up as their
top points of friction giving an example
one of the things that we've found
slowed down teams and developers the
most is
lack of having clear scope and
requirements on their tasks this leads
to
working on the wrong things or working
on things and then discovering that they
weren't designed
appropriately and having to do rework
and so when you when you're looking at
internal developer experience through
the lens of how do you create the most
effective
engineering organization possible
tools may surprisingly not actually be
at the top of the list of opportunities
to actually
drive improvement to
your overall productivity and
performance right what strategies can an
individual team member adopt to improve
his or her dx
that's a great question you know so much
of developer experience is about the
team it's about the shared tools the
shared knowledge the interactions
but as we talked about earlier there's
also this individual element as well
where individuals have their own unique
frustrations and point of friction that
they experience and so there's a few
strategies that
individuals can
employ to improve those one of the
most common we see is what we call job
crafting and that
means that developers actually sort of
tweak
their own roles and job descriptions if
you will to
to meet
the demands of and deal with the
friction that they're encountering and
so a common example of this would be
a senior engineer
who is
wants to get spend more time on
mentoring the team
but is dealing with the frustration of
the balance between their
day-to-day job requirements and
being able to support others and so
someone in this role may actually go to
their manager and have a conversation
about
changing their role slightly to actually
provide them let's say 20 of their time
during the week to block off
to support the rest of the team so you
see this constantly i think on teams
individuals kind of redefining
their role and their expectations in
order to
better
meet the demands of
and needs of their team
and also have a more productive and
satisfying work experience individually
that brings up a very interesting point
you know job crafting seems like a very
valid concept something which can really
improve developer experience but all of
that is based on developers speaking up
and one of the issues that we see
commonly is teams and team members
developers not speaking up and that
reduces the overall engagement which is
very counterproductive to improve dx
and has a overall detrimental effect on
team culture how do you stop this from
happening and if you are in a team where
this is already happening what steps can
be taken
to revert this behavior
well the dynamic you're describing is
extremely common you talk to
teams and
managers all the time where they kind of
jokingly talk about how their meetings
and retrospectives go and it's a lot of
silence not everyone
speaks up and participates and
you know there's an element of that that
is just
somewhat related to the types of
personalities that
are common in engineering but there's
also a big element of that which has to
do with psychological safety and people
feeling comfortable enough to
speak up and
share their honest opinions and thoughts
and that's one of the things
you find with developer experience is
that although there are all these
different
process and tool-related points of
friction
none of those things
matter as much or
can be improved without developers
having a degree of psychological safety
where they feel comfortable speaking
about speaking up about those problems
and or having candid conversations about
how to improve those problems and so
really
enabling developers to speak up
again is i think comes down to
a
creating a culture of psychological
safety both within teams but sometimes
across teams
so developers feel safe doing so and
there's another part of it which is just
that you know not all developers
feel comfortable speaking up in certain
types of social settings so maybe
live meetings isn't the best forum for
developers to voice their concerns so
finding
different methods for developers to be
able to share concerns whether it be
through surveys or through asynchronous
discussions or threads
can really help developers sort of share
their thoughts in a medium through a
channel that feels most comfortable to
them thanks i think that
transitions us into the coping
mechanisms that developers and teams
develop if the strategies to improve dx
do not really work out so what are the
ways coping mechanisms developers can
use with a poor dx
we have industry level data on sort of
how
developer experience affects
things like retention and nutrition and
productivity
but we also
have
insights on what this looks like at the
individual level so
through our research we found that there
are several different common coping
mechanisms or in other words what
developers do when
areas of their developer experience
aren't improved or if developer
experience as a whole
it's not to their satisfaction or isn't
being improved a few of these these are
really funny well some aren't funny but
for example one of the common things
that has come up is a focus on personal
projects so developers
who sort of get frustrated with their
work environment aren't getting as much
fulfillment and satisfaction out of that
so they actually start looking to
personal side projects for that
satisfaction or for that learning right
another
thing related to that is just reduce
engagement so we've seen many developers
who are frustrated with elements of
their work environment simply sort of
become more apathetic and less excited
about their work
and even worse consequence is gaming the
system so we see developers who for
example if they feel like their
estimation process at work is unfair or
if they're being held to unreasonable
deadlines they will intentionally
misreport their estimates to create more
buffer time for themselves
and that of course doesn't serve anybody
especially not the business
and lastly developers often talk about
leaving or looking for new work and we
know from talking to both developers and
leaders that the developer experience is
one of the top reasons why developers
leave it's
not as many people think just about
salaries and pay but it's often about
feeling like they're in an environment
where they just can't get stuff done as
efficiently as they'd like or where
they're
you know not set up to succeed
individually or with their team and so
you know ultimately there are a lot of
sort of coping mechanisms that manifest
themselves before someone leaves but all
of those have
bad consequences for the business and
especially once people leave of course
it's so expensive to find higher
and onboard developers these days that
that presents an enormous challenge to
businesses completely agree with that
the research you are referring to is the
white paper that you have co-authored
titled an actionable framework for
understanding and improving developer
experience i'll make sure we add a link
to that in the show in the podcast notes
that sounds great we'll move on to the
last topic which is around developer
productivity which is one of the key
facets or outcomes out of an improved
developer experience how do you define
developer productivity
wow that is the elusive question of the
last three decades for everyone in
engineering
really developer productivity doesn't
have
any single definition and if you look at
for example the work of one of the
co-authors of this this paper margaret
ann's story she's published dozens and
dozens of papers about this topic of the
differing ways that engineers and
managers and
people in other roles view
productivity one of the interesting
things
that came out of one of our recent
papers
is that developers perception of
productivity
actually
does heavily revolve around their
perception of the amount of output or
the amount of activity for example the
number of tickets they're able to
complete
whereas the perception of managers
actually has a lot more to do with the
performance of the team are they
delivering on their commitments and
projects so
that really highlights how there's
really varying
definitions out there of productivity i
think
if you're asking me individually on my
definition of productivity i believe
that productivity
is ultimately around
how
developers feel
meaning that
because software development is not an
assembly line it's not it's not a factor
where you can just count the widgets
coming out people try right people try
to count
things like lines of code or pull
requests or tickets
but anyone who's in software development
knows these things don't capture the
size or complexity or nuance of that
work and so
they're sort of misleading signals and
so to
really
gauge productivity to me it has to
involve
the perceptions of the developers their
perception on how much is getting done
and when we say perception think of it
as estimation we don't just mean their
high level feelings and intuitions but
their judgment and their estimation of
how much work is getting done and and
whether that amount of good is that
amount of work getting done is
sufficient or good or as good as it
could be so for me
developer productivity is very
perceptual
and that and the perception of
developers the sentiment of developers
is the best signal to understanding how
productive your engineering organization
is that's an interesting way of looking
at productivity so so how would you you
know what would you think are some good
measures for productivity
sure so some examples would be how
much of their time is lost due to
inefficiencies
and that's something that anecdotally
comes up in conversation a lot with
developers in one-on-ones and
when consulting companies come in and do
it you know try to understand what's
slowing down a company but just getting
an estimate on a regular basis from
developers of how much waste there is in
there
system meaning their processes their
tools
that gives you a estimate it's
perceptual but it's it's an estimate no
different than when developers are
estimating how long something will
complete or giving something an
estimated number of points
it's an estimate that's self-reported
based on the expertise of your
developers but that gives you a real
quantifiable
signal right on the amount of
inefficiency and waste in the system
that could be improved and in fact
when we've
run that measure with companies we find
that that number is upwards of 20 or
even 30 percent and when you think about
that in terms of
headcount
right that means that these
organizations have as much opportunity
to improve their output and their
performance by looking internally as
they would hiring 30 20 to 30 more
engineers to do work so i think that
spells
the size of the opportunity again for
leaders to focus and improve developer
experience and what are the commonly
used flawed measures of productivity
that are currently seen across industry
sure
i think the most common ones are of
course the output measures such as lines
of code and number of velocity points i
think more recently you're seeing kind
of a resurgence of those types of
metrics for example number of pull
requests has become a popular metric but
really number of pull requests is no
different than number of lines of code
it has the same flaws and really a pull
request is just a group of commits right
so you're essentially counting something
very similar to commits
i think even going beyond that i spoke
earlier about some of the problems with
process metrics things like lead time
and cycle time you know the problem with
looking at
those types of metrics as
north stars if you will or team level
metrics is that they lack context
there's no single definition of what a
good cycle time or lead time looks like
because it really depends on how a team
works and what they're working on
i think really today both output metrics
and process metrics have flaws and i
think the industry needs to move towards
measuring experience because it really
solves for
the shortcomings of these existing types
of measures thank you a couple of
questions before we wrap up you have
founded a company focusing exclusively
on dx what solution does your company
provide and what is the engagement model
sure dx provides a
solution for any organization that wants
to measure and improve developer
experience we provide a solution that
helps systematically measure over 40
different factors across developer
experience so things like ease of
release test efficiency
uninterrupted time and we provide a
solution that surfaces those metrics not
only for
leadership but for those local teams
because as we discussed earlier it's so
important to provide these types of
measures back to teams so that they can
make their own
local improvements
typically our engagement model
is
that we are brought in by either a cio
or cto or the developer experience team
or the productivity team so someone
pretty high up within an organization
that is either already looking at
developer experience specifically or is
more broadly concerned with just
improving velocity or retention of their
developers
and we partner with these leaders to
implement our solution and also provide
the support that's needed to drive a
program of continual improvement and
measurement to see tangible improvements
and not just developer experience but
those bottom line metrics and signals
we've talked about such as attrition and
output and team performance before we
conclude the catch-all question was
there anything i missed that you would
like to mention no i think you asked her
questions i think we've captured it all
thanks people can follow you on twitter
but how else can people get in touch
people can feel free to connect with me
on twitter or linkedin or just email me
my email address is abinoda at getdx.com
abby thank you for coming on the show
it's been a real pleasure this is
bridget shamanit for software
engineering radio thank you for
listening thanks for having me
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se se-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening